

CURRICULAM VITAE

Plot No: 3 A, Garden Woodroff

Old Pallavarm, Chennai -119 Mobile: 9865129129

Mail:

Dr. Vijayananth Suyamburajan ssvijayananth@gmail.com

Academic Credentials

- Experience in Engineering Education 17 years as on Mar 2020
- Ph.D from Anna University, Chennai Superplastic forming in Composite Materials
- Coordinator for MSME-HIBI (Host Institute for Business Incubations) 2018
- Publications 20
- Book Chapters 3
- Coordinator for First Year Induction Programme by AICTE 2019
- Member in the Syllabus Sub Committee in Anna University Faculty of Mechanical Engineering (2016-17)
- Recognized supervisor Hindustan University, VELs Institute of Science,
 Technology & Advanced Studies (VISTAS)
- D.C Member Anna University, Satyabama University
- Ph.D Guiding 4 Students

Career Summary

S. No	Name of the Institute	Designation	Duration	No of Years
1	VELS Institute of Science, Technology & Advanced Studies	Professor	02-06-2018 - Till Date	2 Year 2 Months
2	Agni College of Technology	Head (Mech & Auto)	01.06.2014 - 31.05.2018	4.5 Years
	MNM Jain Engineering	Asst. Professor	June 10 - Dec 14	4 Years
3	College, Chennai	Lecturer	June 09 – June10	1 Years
4	St. Joseph's College of Engineering, Chennai	Lecturer	Sept 07-May09	2 Years

5	Hindustan College of Engineering, Chennai	Lecturer	Aug 05 – Sept 07	2Years
6	Government College of Engineering, Ti]runelveli.	Lecturer	June 03- Aug 05	2 Year

Industrial Experience

S.N o	Name of the Company	Designation	Duration	No of Years
1	Visha Infotech, Chennai	CAD Engineer	Aug 2000 -May 2001	1 Year

Education

Degree	Date awarded	Institution/ Board	Field of study
Ph.D	DEC 2014	MIT, Chennai	Superplastic Forming
M.E.	DEC 2002	Annamalai University, Chidambaram	Production Engineering
B.E.,	MAY 2000	Arulmigu Kalasalingam College of Engineering, Srivilliputthur	Mechanical Engineering

Patent Filed

Dr. A. Sivakumar, Dr. P. Satishbabu, Dr. V Jayaseelan, Dr. R. Sathyamoorthi, K.

 $\label{eq:main_problem} \textbf{Mallieswaran, Dr. S. VijayAnanth}, \, \textbf{P. Duraimurugan, Dr. P. Balu} \, , \, \text{``Design of }$

Compression Machine for Effective Phase Change of Rapid Auto Ignition", Application

Number: 2019941053865: dated 26/12/2019

Skills Set

Mechanical Packages

i. Design / Modeling : Pro-E, Catia and AutoCAD

ii. Analysis : ABAQUS 6.1

Entrepreneurship Development Cell & Activities Carried out

In-charge for Entrepreneurship development cell from 2016-17

- ✓ Conducted Entrepreneurship awareness program
- ✓ Trained Six students every year in the Entrepreneurship Development cell
- ✓ Member in Tamilnadu EDI (Entrepreneurship Development Institute) and conducting Entrepreneurship development course for first year students(Weekly 3 Hours class) through Wadwani foundation - Trained 75 students in the first year.
- ✓ PM-YUVA Yojana Entrepreneurship Development program conducted for 55 students in the year 2017-18

Responsibilities – College Level

- ✓ Conducted 12 Days First Year Induction program for 250 Students (2019-20) AICTE Program & In charge of First Year induction program (Universal Human Values)
- ✓ NBA Department Coordinator, NAAC Department Coordinator,
- ✓ Head of the Department Mechanical and Automation Engineering (2016-18)
- ✓ NBA Assistant Coordinator
- ✓ Chief superintendent in April-May 2017, Nov-Dec 2018, April-May 2018 Anna
 University Examinations
- ✓ Organizing secretary for College Day and Sports Day 2016-17 & 2017-18
- ✓ Organizing secretary for Teachers Day celebrations 2015-16, 2016-17 & 2017-18
- ✓ Coordinator for College Entrepreneurship Development Cell
- ✓ Graduation day organizing secretary (April 2014)
- ✓ IIT-PALs coordinator (2015-16, 2016-17)

Responsibilities – Department Level

- ✓ Transfer Students in charge, (2018-19, 2019-20, 2020-21)
- ✓ Online Examinations University Question Uploading Department in charge (2020-21)
- ✓ Symposium coordinator VRATILO (March 2015, March 2016 and March 2017)
- ✓ Department NBA Coordinator (2015-16)
- ✓ Convener for one day workshop on Contemporary Approaches on Material Science and Manufacturing, 23.07.2015
- √ HOD In-charge during the period (05.05.2014 26.09.2014)

- ✓ Preparation of NBA Part-II Accreditation in 2012-2013
- ✓ Metrology Lab In-charge 2010-2013
- ✓ Project Coordinator for final year students 2010
- ✓ Class Counselor for 2009 2013
- ✓ Department Placement In-charge 2012-2013
- ✓ Department Time Table In-charge 2005 2007
- ✓ CAD Lab In-charge 2008 2009

Guest Lectures

- ✓ International Webinar Lecture ST JOSEPH UNIVERSITY IN TANZANIA (SJUIT) 11.09.2020
- ✓ Lecture given on First Year Induction program on Universal Human Values 18.08.2019
- ✓ Guest Lecture given on Material Science and Metallurgy on 08-03-2017
- ✓ Resource person for the Faculty Development Training Programme on CE6302 -Mechanics of Solids, sponsored by Anna University on 16.06.2014

Book Chapters

- R. Kumar, Vijay Ananth Suyamburajan, Anish Khan, Abdullah M. Asiri and Hurija Dzudzevic-Cancar, Nanophotocatalysts for hydrogen production applications, Nano materials for Hydrogen Storage Applications, 2020 Elsevier Ltd.
- R. Kumara, P. Senthamaraikannan, S.S. Saravanakumar, Anish Khanc, K. Ganesh, S. VijayAnanth, Polymer Nanocomposite-Based Smart Materials, Electroactive polymer composites and applications, 2020 Elsevier Ltd.
- D. Arthu Jabastine Sundarraj, D. Ananthapadmanaban, K. Arun Vasantha Geethan, VijayAnanth S, Correlation Between Mechanical Properties and Microstructure of Fe-Ti-Zn Alloys Fabricated by Powder Metallurgy, Advances in Micro and Nano Manufacturing and Surface Engineering, Lecture notes on Multi Disciplinary Industrial Engineering, Springer Nature Singapore Pte Ltd, 2019

Publications In International Journal

SanoopSebastian VijayAnanthSuyamburajan, (2020) Microstructural analysis of diffusion bonding on copper stainless steel, Materials Today: Proceedings, (In Press)

- Ajith Arul Daniel, Vijayananth Suyamburajan, Parthiban Alagesan, Sivaganesan Selvaraju (2020) Optimization of machining parameters in electro chemical machining of Al5059/SiC/MoS2 composites using taguchi method, Materials today: proceedings,
- Poovazhagan Lakshmanan, **Vijayananth S***, Sivaganesan S, (2020) Optimizing Ultrasonic Power on Fabricating Aluminum Nanocomposites Reinforced with Boron Carbide Nanoparticles, Materials Science Forum, Vol. 979, pp 28-33
- R. Pugazhenthi , D. Sreeram, S.Vijay Ananth , A. Devaraju, (2020) Surface fracture analysis of stir casted AA 6063/TiC/Gr hybrid composites under different solidification rate, Materials Today: Proceedings, 22 701–704
- V. Jayaseelana, **S. Vijayananth**, J. Francis Xavierc, S. Ajith Arul Daniel, Nallapaneni Manoj Kumard, X.X. Jiange, (2019), Experimental investigation on bi-axial superplastic forming characteristics of AA6063/SiCp with various percentages of SiCp under various temperatures and pressures, Results in Physics, Vol. 15, pp 1-4.
- **Vijayananth S**, Jayaseelan, Ajith Arul Daniel S, Nallapaneni Manoj Kumar, (2019) High temperature superplasticity and its deformation mechanism of AA6063/SiCp, Case Studies in Thermal Engineering, Vol 14, pp. 1-6
- S. Ajith Arul Daniel, R. Pugazhenthi, R. Kumar, **S. Vijayananth,** "Multi objective prediction and optimization of control parameters in the milling of aluminium hybrid metal matrix composites using ANN and Taguchi -grey relational analysis" in Defense Technology (Article in Press)
- **S.Vijayananth** S. Ajith Arul Daniel R K Muthuraman and R. Pugazhenthi (2018) Analysis of Material Removal Rate and Surface Roughness in WEDM Of AL/SIC/MOS2 International Journal of Mechanical Engineering and Technology, Vol 9, (11), pp. 1419–1428
- R. Pugazhenthi R K Muthuraman S. Ajith Arul Daniel and **S.Vijayananth** (2018) Minimizing Production Operation Cycle Time Using Exponential Distribution Heuristic, International Journal of Mechanical Engineering and Technology, Vol 9, (11), pp. 1429–1437.
- S. Ajith Arul Daniel **S.Vijayananth R**. Pugazhenthi R K Muthuraman (2018) Impact Analysis of Insas Rifle Bullet against the Vehicle Auminium, Composite armour plate using LS-DYNA, International Journal of Mechanical Engineering and Technology, Vol 9, (11), pp. 1438–1446.
- J.Immanuel Durai Raj , K.Arun Vasantha Geethan, **S.Vijayananth**, A.John Rajan, (2017), Applied Mathematics, Volume 117 No. 16 2017, 323-331.
- **S. Vijay Ananth,** A. Siddique Ahmed Ghias, M. Dev Anand and G. Glan Devadhas (2016), Experimental Study of Thermal Performance of Coil in Shell Heat Exchanger, Indian Journal of Science and Technology, Vol 9(13), pp 1-17.
- **S. Vijay Ananth,** M. Dev Anand, D. Jackson and N. Prabhu (2016), Investigation of Biodiesel Production from High Free Fatty Acid through RSM, Indian Journal of Science and Technology, Vol 9(13), pp 1-10.

- **S. Vijay Ananth**, V. Jayaseelan and Siva Subramanian, (2014) "Formability Analysis of AA6061 Sheet in T6 Condition" Applied Mechanics of Materials Vol. 766-767, pp. 416-421
- V. Jayaseelan, K. Kalaichelvan, **S. Vijay Ananth**, (2014) Lubrication Effect on Friction Factor of AA6063 in Forward Extrusion Process, <u>Procedia Engineering</u>, Volume 97, 2014, Pages 166–171
- T.Gopal, **S.Vijayananth**, A.Siddique Ahmed Ghias, K. Sudhakar, Simulation of Superplastic Forming Using AA6061 Sheet, International Journal of Applied Engineering Research, Vol. 9 No.26 (2014) pp. 9316-9318
- **S.Vijay Ananth**, K. Kalaichelvan and A. Rajadurai Effect of Thermo Cycling Process in Al6063/SiC_p Composites, European Journal of Scientific Research,ISSN 1450-216X Vol. 88 No 3 October, 2012, pp.403-408
- **S.Vijay Ananth** K. Kalaichelvan and A. Rajadurai, Optimization of Superplastic Forming of Al6063/5%SiC_p Composites Using Taguchi Experimental Design, International Review of Mechanical Engineering (I.RE.M.E.),ISSN 1970-8734, Vol 6. N.6 Sep 2012 pp 1209-1213.
- **S.Vijay Ananth**, M. Kumerasen and K.Kalaichelvan, Effect of Temperature in Superplastic Forming in Al6063/SiC_p, Composites Advanced Materials Research Vols. 538-541 (2012) pp 1111-1114, 2012

Jayaseelan V., Kalaichelvan K., Kannan M., and **Vijay Ananth S** "Extrusion Characteristics of Al/SiC_p by different Manufacturing Process", International Journal of Applied Engineering Research, Vol.1, pp. 194-199. (2010)

Papers presented in National And International Conferences

Arthurjebastine, Arun Vasantha Geethan, **Vijay Ananth S**, (2018) Correlation Between Mechanical Properties And Microstructure Of Fe-Ti-Ni Alloys Fabricated By Powder Metallurgy, AIMTDR 2018 Conference, Anna University, Chennai.

Dhanasekar, **Vijay Ananth S.**, (2013) Analysis of Superplastic forming in Al6063 alloy, Vel's University, Chennai.

Sethuraman, Jayaseelan V and **Vijay Ananth S**, Extrusion analysis of Al6063/SiC Composites, Annamalai University, Chidambaram (2013).

Vijay Ananth S., Chandrasekhar P and K.Kalaichelvan,(2012) Superplastic Forming in Al6063/SiC_P Composites, ICMOC 2012, Noorul Islam University, Thakklai.

Vijayananth S., Ravi S and Kalaichelvan K. (2008), Forming And Analysis In Metal Matrix

Composites Al/SiC, IIT, Madras(Dec-2008)

Ravi S., **Vijayananth S.** and Kalaichelvan K. (2008), "Development and Superplastic forming analysis of Al/SiC composite sheet", National conference on Advances in Robotics, Precision Engineering & Manufacturing Techniques(AIRPAM2008) Madras Institute of Technology, Anna University, pp. 38-43.

Sundaram. S., Anantharaman. N., Ravikumar. K., and Vijay Anand. S. Proceedings of the International

Conference on Mechanical Engineering 2003, (ICME2003) 26- 28 December 2003, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Workshops Attended

- ✓ Two Days Training program on Entrepreneurship Development at Anna University conducted by Tamilnadu EDI
- ✓ One Day workshop on Proposal writing at Rajalaksmi Engineering College
- ✓ One Day Workshop on NPTEL online courses at IIT-Madras
- ✓ Session chair at International Conference in the Department of Mechanical Engineering St.Joseph's Institute of Technology 2016
- ✓ Seven Days FDP on World Class Manufacturing 22.04.2015 to 06.05.2015 RMK College of Engineering, Chennai.
- ✓ Two days workshop on High temperature Ceramics" during 19-20, Feb 2015 held at Department of Ceramic Technology, ACT campus, Anna University, Chennai.
- ✓ Two days Workshop on Applications of Optimization in Research, Saveetha Engineering College, Thandalam (2013).
- ✓ One day Workshop on Metal Forming Process in VIT, Chennai Campus, Dec 2012
- ✓ Faculty Development Programme on Engineering Materials and Metallurgy at MIT Dec 2012
- ✓ Teaching Trainers Programme conducted by NITTR in MNM Jain Engineering
 College on August 2010
- ✓ Faculty Development Programme on Engineering Mechanics at MIT, Dec 2010

Membership Details

\checkmark	Life membership	International	Association	of Engineers	(IAENG)
--------------	-----------------	---------------	-------------	--------------	---------

Personal Details

Name : S. Vijay Ananth

DOB : 10-05-1979

Sex : Male

Marital Status : Married

Permanent Address : No:99/119, Avanangudi Street,

Tisaiyanvillai,

Tirunelveli Dist - 627657

Languages Known: English, Tamil.

I hereby declare that the above written particulars are true to the best of my Knowledge.

Place: Chennai (S. Vijay Ananth)